Something could have to go on
The house is empty, but I can't seem to let it go
Somebody help me, show me how to be alone
I'm almost twenty, but tell me why I feel so old
Yeah, I can't move on, but there's nothing left to hold
Don't think I'll ever go home
I'm not a kid anymore
I'm leaving a piece of my soul
Don't think I'll ever go home
And to my sister, call me when you need some help
You know I'm with you, you're beautiful just as yourself
To the boys that kiss her, you better fucking treat her well
Cause I promised God for her I'd go to hell
Don't think I'll ever go home
I'm not a kid anymore
I'm leaving a piece of my soul
Don't think I'll ever go home
When you're my sister, call me when you need some help
I'm leaving a piece of my soul
I'm leaving a piece of your soul
Don't think I'll ever go home
I'm leaving a piece of my soul
Thank you.